Guide to the Robert P. Anderson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert P. Anderson papers
1880-2014
MS 2035
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.75
(34 boxes)
The papers document the professional and personal life of federal judge and Yale University alumnus Robert P. Anderson. The majority of the collection is comprised of personal papers, including materials from his education at Yale College and Yale Law School, documents related to his service in the United States Coast Guard Reserve, and correspondence with family, friends, and organizations. The second largest portion of the collection consists of materials from his judicial career. These are mainly from his time serving as a judge for the Connecticut Superior Court, the United States District Court, the United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit and the Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals. Also present are materials from government attorney positions. Finally, there is a small number of materials related to his service as a Connecticut State Senator, such as correspondence and campaign materials. Materials date from 1880 to 2014.
Anderson, Robert Palmer, 1906-1978
Scope and Contents
The papers document the professional and personal life of federal judge and Yale University alumnus Robert P. Anderson. The majority of the collection is comprised of personal papers, including materials from his education at Yale College and Yale Law School, documents related to his service in the United States Coast Guard Reserve, and correspondence with family, friends, and organizations. The second largest portion of the collection consists of materials from his judicial career. These are mainly from his time serving as a judge for the Connecticut Superior Court, the United States District Court, the United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit and the Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals. Also present are materials from government attorney positions. Finally, there is a small number of materials related to his service as a Connecticut State Senator, such as correspondence and campaign materials. Materials date from 1880 to 2014.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Personal papers, 1880-2014. II. Connecticut State Senator, 1935-1963. III. Judicial career, 1940-2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert P. Anderson, Jr., 2015
Biographical / Historical
Robert Palmer Anderson was born on March 27, 1906 in Noank, Connecticut. He was the son of Arthur P. Anderson, a probate judge in Groton, Connecticut, and Jessie P. Ashby Anderson. He lived in Noank until he started high school at the Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts. He was admitted into Yale College and graduated in 1927 with a BA in law. He then attended Yale Law School and graduated in 1929 with a LLB in law. He practiced general law with the firm of Waller, Waller, Avery and Gallup in New London, Connecticut, becoming a partner in 1935. In 1934 he was elected Justice of the Peace in Groton, a position he served into the 1940s. In 1936 he was also appointed a United States Commissioner.
After the United States entered World War II, Anderson was commissioned in the United States Coast Guard Reserve as a Lieutenant on January 21, 1942. He served in New London, Connecticut until January 1943. After attending Officers' School in St. Augustine, Florida, he was sent to North Africa in April 1943 as a part of the Lend-Lease Administration. He then was posted in Bizerte, Tunisia as part of the Navy's 8th Amphibious Force, and in the Mediterranean and the English Channel for Flotilla #4 LCI-Ls from May 1943 to November 1943. He was then assigned to the 11th Amphibious Force that participated in the Normandy Invasion, more commonly known as D-Day, until November 1944. Afterwards, he was posted in Washington D.C. as the Chief of the Rescue Vessel and Station Division of Air Sea Rescue at Coast Guard Headquarters and led the Coast Guard reserve unit in New London, Connecticut until he retired in 1957 due to the separation of powers doctrine. He was awarded the Bronze Star Medal by the United States and the Order of the British Empire by the United Kingdom for his service.
Anderson began his work in politics and the state and federal court system in 1936 when he was appointed Public Defender for New London County. In 1946 he was elected to the Connecticut Senate, representing the 18th district. In 1947, he was appointed State's Attorney for New London County. He also served on the military staff Connecticut governors McConaughy, Shannon, and Lodge. He then resigned these positions when he was sworn in as a judge for the Connecticut Superior Court on August 10, 1953. These were succeeded by appointments to the United States District Court in 1954, where he became chief judge in 1960, and to the United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit in 1964. He assumed senior status for the latter in 1971, but went back to active duty in 1972 when the Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals was reformed to exercise judicial rule over an energy price stabilization program. Anderson worked until his death on May 2, 1978, filing his final decision the day before.
Bankruptcy; Jurisprudence; Judges; World War, 1939-1945; Anderson, Robert Palmer, 1906-1978; Connecticut. Superior Court; United States. Court of Appeals (2nd Circuit); United States. District Court (Connecticut); Yale College (1887- ); Yale Law School
- Personal papers, 1880-2014; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises materials documenting the personal information, early life, and family history of Anderson. Biographical materials cover aspects of his life from childhood to his death and include address books, diaries, obituaries and biographical sketches, passports, and religious texts. Correspondence in this series cover a diverse range of subjects. Much of it is with family and friends, but there is a significant amount that focuses on business and community affairs, such as his law practice, properties, and his work with the Marine Historical Society in Mystic, Connecticut. Materials related to his education cover all levels from primary school to post-secondary, with the bulk of materials related to Yale College and Yale Law School. Yale College materials contain coursework and Yale publications while Yale Law School materials almost entirely consist of handwritten class notes. Materials related to his military service focus on his time in the Coast Guard Reserve during World War II and mainly consists of training materials, orders and post assignments, and activities at his different posts, including New London, Connecticut, Portsmouth, England, and Bizerte, Tunisia. There is also a small number of materials related to honors and military awards received, including the Order of the British Empire from the United Kingdom. Finally, there are personal photographs and scrapbooks, mainly of newspaper articles covering events involving Anderson. Materials are from 1880 to 2014, with the bulk from 1927 to the mid-1960s.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged under six headings: biographical materials, correspondence, education, military service, photographs and scrapbooks, and professional associations. Within headings, materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Biographical materials
    - General, 1937-1944, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Address books, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Anderson's personal history, 1906-2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Clippings on Anderson's family, 1963-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diaries, Circa 1928, 1951-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1-15, Box 4)
    - List of some books owned by Robert P. Anderson, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Obituaries, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Official stationaries, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Passports, 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Pistol license, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Religious materials, 1913-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Trips
      - General, 1929-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4-6, Box 5, Folder 1)
      - American Bar Association conference 1971, London, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - British products and sweets, 1961-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Writings on local history, 1935-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence
    - General, incoming, 1950-1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - General, outgoing, 1937-1977 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Anderson, Elizabeth, 1934-1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Anderson, Robert P. and Anderson, Elizabeth helping others, 1957-1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Family, 1880-1976 (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
    - Friends, 1929-1978 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Honors, 1936-05 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Humor, 1948-1978 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Kestrel boat, 1938-1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Law practice, 1930-2010 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Mystic Seaport, 1949-1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Noank, 1949-08-15 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Property, 1935-1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Regarding Anderson's death, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    - Smith, Macauley, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Tengelsen case, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Education
    - Noank Grammar School, Circa 1911 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Phillips Academy, 1919-1978 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Yale College
      - General, 1923-1976 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
      - Calendar, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Freshman year, 1923-1924 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - History of Edwards portrait, 1940-1964 (Box 8, Folder 2, Box 5)
      - Materials for geology course, Circa 1923-circa 1927 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Materials for Latin courses, Circa 1923-circa 1927 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Notes for English courses, Circa 1923-circa 1927 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - Yale Law School
      - General, 1927-1974 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
      - Commencement program, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Examinations, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Legal publications, 1925-1928 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
      - Notes
        - General, Circa 1927-circa 1929 (Box 9, Folder 5-7, Box 10, Folder 1-6)
        - Analysis of cases, Circa 1927-circa 1929 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Connecticut constitution, Circa 1927-circa 1929 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
        - Corporations, Circa 1927-circa 1929 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Real estate, trusts, legal process, evidence, 1925-1929 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
        - Real property, Circa 1927-circa 1929 (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - Torts, Circa 1927-circa 1929 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Reunions, 1964-1974 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Military service
    - Activities, 1943-1944 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General, incoming, 1942-1963 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
      - General, outgoing, 1942-1964 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Admirals Little and Nelson, 1945-1977 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
    - Honors, 1943-1969 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Navigation and Nautical Astronomy, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Newspapers, 1942-1996 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Orders, 1942-1951 (Box 13, Folder 3, Box 5, Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Postings
      - Bizerte, Tunisia, 1943-1958 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
      - Portsmouth, England, 1943-1950 (Box 13, Folder 6, Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Stamps, Undated (Box 21)
    - Training, 1940-1959 (Box 14, Folder 2-5, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20)
  - Photographs and scrapbooks
    - General, 1929-1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Anderson, Robert P., 1909-circa 1969 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Portrait of Robert P. Anderson, Circa 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1959-1966 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Professional associations
    - American Bar Association
      - General, 1937-1948 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Annual meeting in London, England, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Bar examination committee, 1939-1954 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
    - Connecticut Prison Association, 1941-1954 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - New London County Bar Association, 1938-1939, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - State Bar Association of Connecticut, 1939-1959 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Connecticut State Senate, 1935-1963; Series II
  This series comprises materials documenting Anderson's service as a Connecticut State Senator. While there are some materials related to his legislative work with the Senate, the majority of this series consists of campaign materials and correspondence. There are also some files regarding political philosophy and political principles he found relevant. Materials cover from 1935 to 1963.
  Series II is arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming, 1948-1954 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Outgoing, 1948-1953 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Campaign materials, 1940-1963 (Box 22, Folder 3-5)
  - Legislative procedural materials, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Legislative work, 1939-1953 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Political philosophy, 1935-1940, undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Political principles, 1938-1960 (Box 22, Folder 9)
- Judicial career, 1940-2011; Series III
  This series comprises materials documenting Anderson's judgeships, both state and federal. Government attorney positions mostly contain materials related to his position as State Attorney for Connecticut, but it also includes files from his tenure as the Public Defender for New London County and serving on the Governor's military staff. Judgeships include his service on the Connecticut Superior Court, the United States District Court, the United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit, and the Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals. Materials from the Connecticut Superior Court include jury charges, dockets, correspondence and case files. Case files mainly consist of memoranda of decisions. United States District Court files are primarily made up of case files, particularly the New Haven Railroad bankruptcy proceedings, as well as higher profile cases such as Butterworth v. Dempsey and United States v. Silverman. There are also files consisting of law clerk materials, memoranda of decisions, and Judicial Conference files. United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit materials contain files on various court issues, such as comments on Anderson's rulings and reports on extra-judicial income, as well as a full index of cases heard by Anderson and correspondence. Records related to his service on Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals are limited and include some of his draft opinions. Materials cover from 1940 to 2011, with the bulk of materials from 1940 to 1975.
  Series III is arranged under two headings: government attorney positions and judgeships. Within headings, materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Government attorney positions
    - Public defender, New London County, 1940-1947 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - State Attorney
      - General, 1947-1953 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Connecticut Turnpike, 1952-1953 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1948-1953 (Box 23, Folder 4-6)
    - Governor's military staff
      - General, 1944-1956 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Eisenhower's inauguration, 1953 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Judgeships
    - Connecticut Superior Court
      - General
        - 1953-1957 (Box 23, Folder 9-10)
        - Dockets, 1953-1954 (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
      - Case files
        - General memoranda of decisions, 1953-1954 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - Adams v. Greenwich Water Company, 1953 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1944-1954 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - Jury charges
        - Civil charges, Undated (Box 24, Folder 6-7, Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Civil charges, part I, revised by Comley, J., Undated (Box 25, Folder 2-3)
        - Civil charges, part II, revised by Comley, J., Undated (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
        - Civil charges, part III, revised by Comley, J, Undated (Box 25, Folder 6, Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Civil charges, part I, revised by Maltbie, C.J., Undated (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
        - Civil charges, part II, revised by Maltbie, C.J., Undated (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
        - Criminal charges, revised by Comley, J., Undated (Box 26, Folder 6, Box 27, Folder 1)
        - Criminal charges, part I, revised by Maltbie, C.J., Undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - Criminal charges, part II, revised by Maltbie, C.J., Undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - General principles, Undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Newspapers, 1946-1953 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - United States District Court
      - General, 1947-1965, 2011 (Box 27, Folder 6-7)
      - Correspondence
        - General, incoming, 1936-1977 (Box 27, Folder 8, Box 28, Folder 1)
        - General, outgoing, 1954-1964 (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - Anderson's review of 1953-1964 (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - Regarding Learned Hand, 1958-1976 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Case files
        - Buckley v. Hoff, 1963-1965 (Box 28, Folder 5)
        - Butterworth v. Dempsey
          - General, 1963-1965 (Box 28, Folder 6-9)
          - Comments, 1964-1966 (Box 28, Folder 10)
        - Johnson v. Sanders, 1969-1970 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - New Haven Railroad bankruptcy
          - General, 1957-1980 (Box 29, Folder 2-3)
          - Anderson's personal file, 1964-1977 (Box 29, Folder 4)
          - Appointment of trustees, 1960-1965 (Box 29, Folder 5)
          - History of the New Haven Railroad, 1962 (Box 29, Folder 6)
          - Investigation and report, 1963 (Box 29, Folder 7)
          - Newspaper clippings, 1956-1971 (Box 29, Folder 8-9, Box 30, Folder 1-4)
          - Plans for reorganization filed by public, 1961-1965 (Box 30, Folder 5)
        - United States v. Silverman
          - General, 1985 (Box 30, Folder 6)
          - Newspaper clippings, 1955-1956 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      - Government publications, 1954-1965 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - Hartford Federal Courthouse, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - Judicial Conference files, 1955-1964 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Law clerks, 1954-1982, 2007 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Memoranda of decisions, 1954-1964 (Box 31, Folder 3-6)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1954-1960 (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Photographs, 1962 (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - Scrapbook, 1961-1966 (Box 32, Folder 3-4)
      - Stationery, Undated (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit
      - Correspondence
        - General, incoming, 1956-1978 (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
        - General, outgoing, 1965-1977 (Box 32, Folder 8)
        - Biltmore Hotel, 1971-1977 (Box 32, Folder 9)
        - Congratulatory messages, 1964 (Box 32, Folder 10, Box 33, Folder 1-2)
        - Medina, Harold R., 1964-1979 (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Court issue files
        - General, 1955-1976 (Box 33, Folder 4)
        - Comments on Anderson's rulings, 1964-1976 (Box 33, Folder 5)
        - Connecticut occupational tax, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 6)
        - Judicial conferences, 1964-1977 (Box 33, Folder 7)
        - Marriage ceremony, Undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
        - Public report of extra-judicial income, 1969-1977 (Box 33, Folder 9)
        - United States courts versus English courts, 1965 (Box 33, Folder 10)
      - Index of cases heard by Anderson, 1964-1977 (Box 33, Folder 11, Box 34, Folder 1-3)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1954-1974 (Box 34, Folder 4-5)
      - Photographs, 1962-1964, Undated (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Temporary Emergency Court of Appeals
      - General, 1961-1972 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      - Anderson's opinions, 1972-1975 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence regarding library materials, 1972-1974 (Box 34, Folder 9)